<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Oauths on WHMCS Developer Documentation</title>
    <link>//developers.whmcs.com/oauth/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Oauths on WHMCS Developer Documentation</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="//developers.whmcs.com/oauth/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>OAuth</title>
      <link>//developers.whmcs.com/oauth/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//developers.whmcs.com/oauth/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OAuth enables third-party applications to obtain limited access to the WHMCS service on behalf of users.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <link>//developers.whmcs.com/oauth/introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//developers.whmcs.com/oauth/introduction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you have an app or service that needs to interact with WHMCS on behalf of your users, you should use OAuth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WHMCS uses OAuth 2, an open specification, which allows users to authenticate with WHMCS to both verify their identity and give your app permission to access their data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once authorization is completed by a user, the OAuth process returns an access token to your app. The access token is a string generated by the WHMCS instance that you&amp;rsquo;ll need to send with each subsequent API request to uniquely identify both your app and the end user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several reasons we use OAuth. Most importantly, your app doesn&amp;rsquo;t need to store or transmit the user&amp;rsquo;s WHMCS password. OAuth also allows the user to authorize only a limited set of permissions and the user may revoke access at any time. This makes OAuth a safer and more secure form of API authorization for your users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;notice info&#34; &gt;&lt;p&gt;OAuth is an open protocol we support in WHMCS for allowing third-party applications to obtain limited access to the WHMCS service on behalf of users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Authentication Workflow</title>
      <link>//developers.whmcs.com/oauth/auth-workflow/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//developers.whmcs.com/oauth/auth-workflow/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here’s how the process typically works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;User presses a “Connect to WHMCS” button inside your app.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your app redirects the user to the WHMCS installation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The user logs into WHMCS and authorizes your app to access their WHMCS account using the permissions your app has requested.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After the user approves your app, they’ll be redirected back to your app with an authorization code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your app can then use this authorization code to make a request for a re-usable access token which can be used to make subsequent requests to the WHMCS API. This takes place in the background and should not be visible to end users.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All OAuth requests require a valid API Client Credential Identifier and Secret. Credentials for OpenID connect can be created via the OpenID Connect admin interface. For Single Sign-On credentials, we recommend using the Provisioning Module API for Application Links. Alternatively, you can provision and manage OAuth Client Credentials via the WHMCS API.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>API Commands</title>
      <link>//developers.whmcs.com/oauth/api/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//developers.whmcs.com/oauth/api/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The following API commands exist for interacting with OAuth/OpenID Connect credentials in WHMCS:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ListOAuthCredentials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CreateOAuthCredential&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UpdateOAuthCredential&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DeleteOAuthCredential&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Further Reading</title>
      <link>//developers.whmcs.com/oauth/further-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//developers.whmcs.com/oauth/further-reading/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For more information, please refer to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OpenID Connect User Guide&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OpenID Connect Developer Guide&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>